Finding Aid for Committee For Responsible Tax Reform records, 1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Committee For Responsible Tax Reform records 1989
Committee For Responsible Tax Reform.
1 linear foot.
91430 Bj 2
Michigan citizens group established in support of proposal B relating to the reform of public school financing on the 1989 state ballot. Reports, surveys, minutes, correspondence, and audio and visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was acquired from the organization in July of 1990. (Donor No. 7837 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Committee for Responsible Tax Reform (CRTR) was formed in 1989 to promote Proposal B on the November ballot. The campaign was directed by John D. Marrs of Williamston, Michigan. Its offices were located at the headquarters of the Michigan Association of School Administrators in Lansing, Michigan.
In the November election voters were faced with two proposals that would reform public school financing. Both proposals would have increased the states sales tax: Proposal A up 1/2 cent and Proposal B up 2 cents. Both proposals were defeated.
According to the Committee on Responsible Tax Reform Proposal B would have reduced school taxes on residential and farm property statewide by an average of 38% and taxes on business property by 23%. It would have also provided at least three hundred forty dollars in new revenue per pupil to 85% of the states K-12 school districts. This proposal was supported strongly by Representatives Glenn Oxlander (Republican-Sturgis), Micheal E. Nye (Republican-Litchfield), William R. Keith (Democrat-Garden City), and James A. Kasteva (Democrat-Canton).
The records of CRTR consist of one foot of materials from the campaign office dating from 1989. The materials consist of reports, surveys, minutes, and correspondence. Most of the reports and surveys were not produced by CRTR but by other organizations that were concerned about school taxes. These records were kept by CRTR mostly as reference materials to assist them in their campaign. The correspondence and committee records were produced by CRTR but are very few in number.
This record group also contains some audio and visual materials. The cassette tape found in the folder labeled program tape is part of a slide presentation made by CRTR. The visual material is a video cassette of a commercial opposing the passage of Proposal B and is narrated by L. Brooks Patterson.
Subjects:
Committee for Responsible Tax Reform.; Education--Finance.; Elections--Michigan--1989.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Taxation--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Political elections--1989.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Organizational records
  - Brochures
    - Committee (Box 1)
    - Others (Box 1)
  - Campaign
    - Coalition Building and Campaign Planning (Box 1)
    - Finance Requirements (Box 1)
    - Organization (Box 1)
    - Strategy (Box 1)
  - Citizens Research Council of Michigan (Box 1)
  - Citizens Unfairly Taxed (proposal) (Box 1)
  - Contributors (to CRTR) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Fiscal information (comparing proposals A & B) (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Chamber of Commerce (Box 1)
  - Headlee, Richard (Box 1)
  - House of Representatives (Michigan)
    - Fiscal Report (Box 1)
    - Joint Resolution I (Box 1)
  - Intermediate school districts (Box 1)
  - Maisa survey (Box 1)
  - Michigan Association of School Administrators (Box 1)
  - Michigan Board of Education (Box 1)
  - Michigan Education Association
    - Frequency Questionnaire (Box 1)
    - Support for Proposal A (Box 1)
  - Michigan Municipal League (Box 1)
  - Middle Cities Education Association (Box 1)
  - News releases (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Per pupil spending projections (Box 1)
  - Positions of organizations (Box 1)
  - Printed materials
    - Blanchard, James J., "Michigan Schools of Tomorrow," 1989 (Box 1)
    - Gongwer News Service, "Reports," 1989 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Board of Education, Operation Outreach (Box 1)
    - "Opinions of Michigan Citizens about Community Colleges," 1989 (Box 1)
    - "Opinions of Michigan Citizens about Public Schools," 1989 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Department of Management and Budget, "Preparing Our Children: A Report on Education Investment in Michigan," 1981 (Box 1)
    - Michigan State Chamber of Commerce, "Michigan Forward," 1989 (Box 1)
  - Program scripts (Box 1)
  - Program tapes (Box 1)
  - Promote Michigan Education Committee (Box 1)
  - Proposal A (Box 1)
  - Proposal B
    - General (Box 1)
    - Supporters (Box 1)
  - Requests for information (for CRTR) (Box 1)
  - Senate (Michigan)
    - Fiscal Report (Box 1)
  - State Chamber of Commerce (Box 1)
  - Steering Committee (Box 1)
  - Videotape commercial
    - "Citizens Against $400 Million Sales Tax Increase." (narrated by L. Brooks Patterson) (Box 1)
  - Video Tape Script (Produced By CRTR) (Box 1)